Finding Aid for Middle English Dictionary records, 1925-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Miscellaneous MED Materials
  - Audio, Digital, and Visual Materials, and Artifacts
    Additional visual materials are housed in Box 74, including four printed maps of England (all or part) used by the editors, and six examples of camera-ready pages for the MED, to illustrate the various stages the printed fascicles went through between 1952 and 2001. These are: E.1 e -- endelonges (1952), the first fascicle to be printed; the original Plan and Bibliography (1954); N.1 muche -- neigh (1978), a late example of typewriter-composited copy; Q q -- raiment (1984), the first word-processed fascicle; S.13 spranklinge -- steering (1990), a late example of the word-processed format used from Q through S; and T.1 t -- tasting (1993), the first fascicle with formatting changes to increase readability (boldfaced dates, italicized short titles for Middle English texts, etc.).
    An MED Sorting Board is also part of the Audio, Digital, and Visual Material, and Artifacts series. Because of its size (26" high, 33" wide, and 11" deep at the bottom) it is housed separately. This particular sorting board was created by MED associate editor Oscar Johnson in the 1940s, and thereafter each editor had one like it at his or her desk for use in editing: usually, as the first step, for sorting the quotation slips for a word by date, with a slot for each century or part of a century; then, for separating senses or subsenses, with tentative definitions clipped to the backs of the slots into which the illustrative quotations were dropped; next, as the interpretation of senses was refined, for separating the contents of one slot into two or three, or for combining the contents of more than one slot into a single one; and, ultimately, for having the whole word in question arranged and labeled in final form by senses and subsenses along with the relevant quotations for each.
    - Audio Material
      - Remarks by Professor James W. Downer at Sherman M. Kuhn's retirement party June 2, 1983, 1 audiocassettes (Box 73)
      - Interview with Professor Larry Benson about Chaucer on NPR's Morning Edition, with comments on the MED, April 2, 1987 (, 1 audiocassettes (Box 73)
      - "Alphabet Odyssey," a program on the MED produced by Cindy Bisaillon on the Canadian Broadcasting Co.'s radio program Ideas, October 4, 2004, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 73)
    - Audio-Visual Material
      - Vice President Homer Neal's Presentation to the University of Michigan Board of Regents,"Research at the University of Michigan," with a brief segment on the MED, 1994 (Box 73)
    - Digital Material
      - Glossarial database circa 1980s-1990s, 4 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 73)
      - Transcriptions of Trev. Higd., Trev. Dial.LC, and Trev. Epistle Berkeley in Hnt HM 28561 circa 1980s-1990s, 2 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 73)
      - Text of Warner's edition of Vsp.D.Hom., ca. 1980s-1990s, 1 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 73)
      - Quotations for MED Supplement prepared during grant from OVPR in summer of 2001, 2008, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 73)
      - Copy of online Middle English Compendium 2008, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 73)
    - Visual Material
      - Drawing (pen and ink) of the Exterior of 555 South Forest by Michael Klement presented to Lewis by First Martin Corporation 2001 (Box 73)
      - Facsimiles of Miscellaneous Medieval Manuscript Illustrations 1930s-1960s (Box 73)
      - Photographs
        - Miscellaneous Photographs (3 sets) 1930s-2001 (Box 73)
          (for other photographs see Retirements and Obituaries folders in Box 16)
        - Kurath and unknown participants in Summer Linguistic Institute at University of Michigan, taken in 5005 Angell Hall, ca. late 1940s (Box 73)
        - The five chief editors of the MED, for use in the 2001 exhibition in the University of Michigan Graduate Library, 1930s-2001 (Box 73)
        - MED offices at 555 South Forest and members of the staff, 2001 (Box 73)
        - MED Staff in Angell Hall, early 1960s (Box 73)
      - Postcards of British Museum Manuscripts
        - circa 1930s-1940s (Box 73)
        - circa 1930s-1940s (Box 73)
      - Slides of Medieval Manuscripts, Editions of Medieval Texts, and MED Entries Used by Kurath for Presentation to Research Club, University of Michigan, November 1954 (Box 73)
        (1n 2 slide boxes)
      - Transparencies of Medieval Manuscripts circa 1960s-1970s (Box 73)
    - Artifacts
      - IBM Typewriter Balls (2) with letters or diacritics for use in MED, 1952-1984 (Box 73)
      - MED Stamp, 1930s-2001 (Box 73)
      - Keys to Angell Hall 5005, 1930s-1975 (Box 73)
      - MED Sorting Board
    - Visual Material
      (additional materials in Box 73)
      - Printed Maps (Box 74)
        - Student's Outline Map of Historical England, 1888 (with numbered dialect placements in pencil) (Box 74)
        - Dialect Map of England, from Moore, Meech, and Whitehall, "Middle English Dialect Characteristics and Dialect Boundaries," 1935 (Box 74)
        - Monastic Britain, South Sheet 1954 (Box 74)
        - Britain before the Conquest, South Sheet 1973 (Box 74)
      - Samples of Final Camera-Ready Pages (6 packages each wrapped in brown paper, with earliest at the bottom)
        - E.1 e -- endelonges (1952): the first fascicle to be printed (Box 74)
        - The original Plan and Bibliography (1954) (Box 74)
        - N.1 muche -- neigh (1978): a late example of typewriter composited copy (Box 74)
        - Q q -- raiment (1984): the first word-processed fascicle (Box 74)
        - S.13 spranklinge -- steering (1990): a late example of the word-processed format used from Q through S (Box 74)
        - T.1 t -- tasting (1993): the first fascicle with formatting changes to increase readability (boldfaced dates, italicized short titles for Middle English texts, etc.) (Box 74)
  - Hand-Pulled Cross-References, late 1940s to 1980s/early 1990s
    The Hand-Pulled Cross Reference cards series (box 75) is held in the first half of Box 75, and contains a sample of the cross-references (A-En, W-Z) that were used from the late 1940s through the 1980s, and even into the early 1990s, before the MED had developed a program to insert them directly from the computerized copy. These cross-references were hand-pulled from both the handwritten copy and the first draft of the composited copy, typed on slips, and then inserted into the final composited copy.
    - A -- En, W -- Z (Box 75)
  - Quotations
    The remaining three and a half boxes in MISCELLANEOUS MED MATERIALS (the remainder of 75 through box 78) are made up of the Quotations series, that contains primarily quotations which were donated to, or in a few cases prepared at, the MED but which were not used in the current printed or online dictionaries. These consist of: Concordance Slips forAvowing of Arthur, Stern Quotations, Cornish Quotations, Cornell Class B Material and MED Reading Program slips.
    Concordance Slips for Avowing of Arthur (half of box 75) were sent to the MED in 1939 by Norman Waldorf of San Jose, California. They are alphabetically arranged.
    The Stern Quotations (box 76-77) are quotations sent to the MED by Professor Gustav Stern of G旦teborg in the 1940s, containing miscellaneous words; alphabetically arranged.
    Cornish Quotations (box 77); alphabetically arranged. In letters G through P (1963-1984) of the MED Cornish quotations from Origo Mundi and Pass.Christi in Norris Anc.Corn.Drama that contained words borrowed from Middle English were included, but this practice was discontinued beginning with Q (1984); in addition to the unused Cornish quotations, this part of box 77 also contains notes on where in the MED (G through P) Cornish quotations may be found.
    Cornell Class B Material (box 78) contains a selection only. The titles given are a combination of titles in the Cornell material and the short titles in the Plan and Bibliography, 2nd edition. Editors Meech, Whitehall, and Rettger, in a report of September 30, 1934, after Moore's death, observed that of the 219,000 quotation slips sent to the MED from Cornell in 1930, 105,000 "were of such slight value because the words recorded on them were adequately represented in the Oxford material and because quotations in them were short or altogether lacking that we put them aside and probably will never touch them again." The MED referred to these slips as "Cornell Class B Material," and this category also contained those of the additional quotations sent from Cornell in 1942 that were not filed in the boxes during 1942-1943.
    MED Reading Program (in the center of box 78) comprises a small number of slips taken from the Doncaster Corporation manuscript, prepared at an unknown date; arranged by page.
    - Concordance Slips for Avowing of Arthur (1 1/2" x 5" slips, in two rows, one on top of the other)
      - A -- K (top row of slips) (Box 75)
      - L -- Z (bottom row of slips) (Box 75)
    - "Stern Quotations" (4" x 6 1/2" slips) (Box 76)
      - Quotations for words beginning with a through rad- (Box 76)
      - Quotations for words beginning with rak-through y (Box 77)
    - Cornish Quotations (4 1/4" x 7 1/4" slips) (Box 77)
    - "Cornell Class B Material," 1939 1942-43 (Box 78)
      - 3" x 5" Cards
        - Mandeville (1) (alphabetical H--Yogh: catchwords only); Henley Husbandry (alphabetical) (Box 78)
        - Rolle Mending of Life (by page/line number) (Box 78)
        - Lydgate Aesop (Ashm & Trin-C [Archiv 85]) (alphabetical) (Box 78)
        - Claudian CS (by line number) (Box 78)
        - Maidstone Seven Penitential Psalms (Englische Studien 10) (by line number) (Box 78)
        - Partonope of Blois (2) (by line number) (Box 78)
        - A Pennyworth of Wit (by line number) (Box 78)
        - Rolle MPass.(1) (Englische Studien 7) (by line number) (Box 78)
        - Ailred Inform. (alphabetical) (Box 78)
        - Bot fals men (by line number) (Box 78)
        - Lai le Freine (alphabetical) (Box 78)
        - Vices and Virtues(1) (by page/line number: catchwords only) (Box 78)
        - Ordin.Nuns (1), 1st reading (by page/line number: catchwords only) (Box 78)
        - Ordin.Nuns (1), 2nd reading (alphabetical: D--I words only) (Box 78)
      - 4 1/4" x 7 1/4" Slips
        - Ordin.Nuns (1), 3rd reading (by page/line number) (Box 78)
    - MED Reading Program (4 1/4" x 7 1/4" slips)
      - Doncaster Corporation MS, from Antiq. 19, pp. 263-65 (by page) (Box 78)
- Non- MED MATERIALS
  The subgroup NON- MED MATERIALS consists of material relating mainly to the Early Modern English Dictionary (EMED). For many years after the postponement of the EMED in 1939 in favor of the MED, it was hoped that work on the EMED could resume after the MED was completed, but that hope was abandoned and the quotation slips and related materials were sent to Oxford University Press in 1994 for use in the third edition of the OED (in progress). Thirteen boxes (79-91) are all that remain at the University of Michigan of the materials from the EMED. These materials are primarily from the 1930s (with one exceptions in boxes 87-91) and are almost exclusively bibliographical.
  The NON- MED MATERIALS subgroup consists of two series: Bibliographies and Holdings Lists and Manuscript Concordances and Collections by Charles Crawford.
  - Bibliographies and Holdings Lists
    This first series, Bibliographies and Holdings Lists, series includes eight files: Master Bibliography of Early Modern English Texts, Early Modern English Texts and Reference Works in the Former EMED Library, Clements Library Early Modern English Holdings, Law Library Early Modern English Holdings, Books Housed in the Former MED Library for the Use of the EMED, General Bibliography in the Former EMED Library, and Selective List of Early Modern English Suffixes. Materials in all sub-series are arranged alphabetically.
    - Master Bibliography of Early Modern English Texts 1930s
      The file Master Bibliography of Early Modern English Texts sub-series comprises the first six and a half boxes (79 through the first half of 85). It contains a master bibliography of Early Modern English texts.
      - A -- Cam (Box 79)
      - Can -- Dul (Box 80)
      - Dum -- Hd (Box 81)
      - Hea -- Marq (Box 82)
      - Marr -- Rann (Box 83)
      - Rao --Tol (Box 84)
      - Tom --Z (Box 85)
    - Early Modern English Texts and Reference Works in the EMED Library, 1930s
      The file Early Modern English Texts and Reference Works in the Former EMED Library (box 85) consists of index cards of the EMED Library holdings.
      - A -- Y (Box 85)
    - Clements Library Early Modern English Holdings 1930s
      The Clements Library Early Modern English Holdings file (box 86) contains index cards listing the Early Modern English holdings at the University of Michigan's Clements Library.
      - A -- Z (Box 86)
    - Law Library Early Modern English Holdings 1930s
      The Law Library Early Modern English Holdings file consists of index cards listing the Early Modern English holdings in the University of Michigan Law Library.
      - A -- Z (Box 86)
    - Books Housed in the Former MED Library for the Use of the EMED, 1930s
      The Books Housed in the Former MED Library for the Use of the EMED fileconsists of index cards from the 1930s detailing EMED holdings in the MED library. They are chiefly from the 1930s.
      - A -- W (Box 86)
    - General Bibliography in the Former EMED Library, 1930s
      The first half of box 87 contains the General Bibliography in the Former EMED Library sub-series, along with an index to it.
      - A-Y (Box 87)
    - Index to the General Bibliography 1930s
      - A -- W (Box 87)
    - Selective List of Early Modern English Suffixes 1930s
      The second half of the box contains the sub-series Selective List of Early Modern English Suffixes, with examples of words ending with the suffixes. These suffixes are alphabetically arranged, from --lent to --ous. It is unclear whether any further examples were in the EMED files.
      - Suffixes from-lent to-ous (Box 87)
  - Manuscript Concordances and Collections by Charles Crawford
    The second series, Manuscript Concordances and Collections by Charles Crawford, comprises four boxes (88 through 91), containing ten files (with varying numbers of manuscript volumes in each, for a total of 27 volumes), arranged alphabetically by manuscript title: Avisa Series I, Avisa Series II, Belvedere, A Breton Concordance, a Concordance to Ben Jonson's Works, a Concordance to John Lyly's Euphues, an Index to Wits Treasury, a Concordance and Index to "Lines of Poems by Surrey, Wyatt and authors in Tottel's Miscellany," a Miscellaneous Volume, and a Concordance to The Paradise of Dainty Devices.
    The writer of nearly all of these volumes was Charles Crawford, though how they made their way into the EMED Library is unknown. Crawford was a journalist of some kind, as well as a private scholar; he was born in Manchester in 1860 and lived and worked in London. From documents in the OED archives, Crawford was suggested for work on the dictionary in 1902, and was offered a position, but decided to withdrew because he felt he was not well enough qualified. He did give occasional help and advice to the OED in the years following, and it may be that the present volumes came to the EMED along with the Early Modern English slips donated by the OED in the late 1920s and early 1930s.
    As a scholar and critic, Crawford flourished during the last decade of the 19th century and the first three decades of the 20th century. He began publishing articles on Elizabethen writings in the 1890's chiefly in the journal Notes & Queries and continued writing articles on related subjects at least through 1929; two volumes of the early articles appeared in his Collectanea in 1906 and 1907. He edited England's Parnassus in 1913 and published concordances of the works of Thomas Kyd (1906-10) and Christopher Marlowe (1911-32). His manuscript volumes in the EMED Library date from between 1895 and "after 1929," though most were written between 1914 and 1929.
    Box 88 contains the first sub-series Avisa Series I (four volumes), and the second, Avisa Series II (three volumes). These are collections of English verse (primarily) and some prose of the late 16th and early 17th centuries, with pages consecutively numbered within each sub-series.
    The third sub-series Belvedere, or The Garden of the Muses, comprises three volumes and is contained in the first half of Box 89. This is a collection of quotations from the compilation entitled Belvedere (1600), edited by John Bodenham, arranged by subject, in three volumes, with pages consecutively numbered.
    The second half of Box 89 contains volumes 1 through 4 of the fourth sub-series A Breton Concordance. This is a concordance to the works of Nicholas Breton (1545-1626) and others in eleven volumes and is based on the quotations presented in the seven volumes of Avisa Series I and Avisa Series II in Box 88.
    Box 90 contains the remaining seven volumes (5 through 11) of the fourth sub-series A Breton Concordance
    Box 91 contains the fifth through the tenth sub-series. The fifth is "A Concordance to the 1616 Folio edition of Ben Jonson's Works, and the first edition of Every Man in his Humour." This is in fact primarily a word index based on Crawford's own concordance (not here); in his table of "Contents" Crawford refers to it as "A synopsis of the Concordance."
    The sixth sub-series contains primarily a concordance to John Lyly's Euphues: The Anatomy of Wyt. Euphues was first published in 1578, but this concordance is based on Edward Arber's edition published in 1868 or, more likely, the later reprint of it in 1895.
    The seventh sub-series is an Index to "Wits Treasury, 1598." Palladis Tamia, Wits Treasury was written by Francis Meres (1565-1647); Crawford's volume is a combined subject index and concordance, but the primary emphasis is on subjects and proper names.
    The eighth sub-series is entitled "Lines of Poems by Surrey, Wyatt and authors in Tottel's Miscellany and other places arranged in alphabetical order"; it is in fact both a separate concordance and an index of words in these authors.
    The ninth sub-series is a miscellaneous volume, written by both Crawford and others, containing an edition of a play by Robert Armin, a fragmentary concordance to Hamlet, various subject-indexes to England's Parnassus (1600), and a fragmentary list of English names and writings mentioned in Robert Burton's Anatomy of Melancholy
    The tenth sub-series is a concordance to various editions between 1576 and 1600 of The Paradise of Dainty Devices. Most of The Paradise of Dainty Devices was probably compiled by Richard Edwards (?1523-66), though poems by other, later writers were included in the editions.
    - Avisa Series I
      (On the flyleaf (unnumbered) of Volume I: "Charles Crawford/ London/ June 1st, 1928." Unless noted, the texts are on the odd-numbered pages (with short notes in the righthand margins), often preceded by introductory matter on both odd-and even-numbered pages; longer notes are on the even-numbered pages; and some pages are blank, primarily even-numbered ones, as well as occasional odd-numbered ones at the ends of texts)
      - Volume I (pp. 1-475) (Box 88)
        Notes by Crawford on Nicholas Breton (3 unnumbered pages at the beginning, followed by some blank pages)
        Henry Willoby Willobie His Avisa (1594): pp. 1-279N
        Peter Colse Penelope's Complaint or A Mirrour for wanton Menions (1596): pp. 282-407
        Constant Penelope. A Looking-glass for Ladies (no date) (a ballad copied from Percy's Reliques of Ancient English Poetry, 3rd series, book 3, no. 10 [1802]): pp. 408-17
        The Ballad of Constant Susanna (no date): pp. 418-29
        Extract from The Phoenix Nest (1593): pp. 430-45; specifically (pp. 433-45), the "Apology for the Earl of Leicester,"Crawford's title for The Dead Mans Right,Written upon the death of the Right Honorable the Earle of Leicester
        George Gascoigne, "Extracts from the 1573 'Posies'" [Crawford's short title for] A Hundreth sundrie Flowres bounde up in one small Poesie (1573): pp. 446-75; from p. 468 to p. 475 is "Miscellaneous matter in the 1573 Quarto omitted in the 'Posies' of 1575"
      - Volume II (pp. 476-935) (Box 88)
        A -- George Gascoigne, "Extracts from the 1573 'Posies'": (continued from Volume I), ending with Crawford's note: "End of Extracts from 1573 Quarto omitted altogether or altered in the edition of 1575": pp. 476-93)
        B -- Brief extracts from various authors and works, scattered throughout the rest of the volume on the following pages (pp. 493A935O):
        William Shakespeare: pp. 493A-B: Dedication to the Sonnets (1609); pp. 493C-F: Address to the Reader from the 1609 Quarto of Troilus and Cressida; (copied from The Shakespeare Allusion-Book, I.207-8); pp. 527-29: "[Stalling the Deer]," Extract from The Passionate Pilgrime (1599))
        Nicholas Breton: (pp. 494-97: Extract from "The Countess of Pembroke's Love" (1592); pp. 534-39, 550-59, 642-43; 672-73, 817A-97: Extracts from The Arbor of Amorous Devices (1597); pp. 540-47, 560-87, 640-41, 668-71, 682-89, 699C-701, 706-31, 738-45, 746-49, 750-53, 766-95: Extracts from Brittons Bowre of Delights (1597); pp. 588-95, 606-11, 674-81, 690-95, 899-935: Extracts from Daffodils and Primroses (1593); pp. 646-51: Extract from A Post with a Packet of Madde Letters (1603/1637); pp. 652-67: Extracts from The Toyes of an Idle Head (1582); pp. 761A-H: Extracts from The Wil of Wit (1599)
        Sir Philip Sidney(Extracts from the Arcadi a: pp. 498-501: "Sapphics" from the 1590 edition; pp. 795A-795B: two sonnets added to the 1598 edition)
        Francis Davison (Extracts from A Poetical Rapsody (1602): pp. 500-503: "Sapphics upon the Passion of Christ" (copied from A.H. Bullen's edition [1890-91], 2.97); pp. 506-507A: "Ode XI: To his Muse" (from Bullen, 2.68); pp. 612-39: "An Eclogue Made long since upon the Death of Sir Philip Sidney" (from Bullen, 1.63) and "An Epigram to Sir Philip Sidney in Elegiacal Verse," "Hexameters upon the never-enough praised Sir Philip Sidney," "Another upon the same,", "Others upon the same (from Bullen, 2.90-92))
        Extracts from The Phoenix Nest (1593 all copied from Heliconia, ed. T. Park [1815]):(pp. 504-505: "Sapphics"; pp. 530-33: "[Cleopatra's Adders.] 'A Counterlove'"; pp. 600-605: "Elegies on Sir Philip Sidney"; pp. 696-99: "A Most Excellent Passion Set downe by N.B. Gent.")
        [J. Bodenham]: pp. 508-13: "Fair Phyllis and her Shepherd," Extract from England's Helicon (1600)
        [John Lyly]: pp. 514-25D: "[Women, like castles, are to be won with perseverance]" (from R.W. Bond's edition The Complete Works [1902-10], III.459)
        William Byrd, Extracts from First Book of Psalms, Sonnets, and Songs of Sadness and Piety (1588): pp. 596-99: "The Funeral Songs of that Honourable Gentleman, Sir Philip Sidney, Knight" (copied from A.H. Bullen's Shorter Elizabethan Poems, pp. 22-23); pp. 702-705: "[The rest are all disgraced]," "[A Sonet of faire womens fickleness in love]" (from Bullen, pp. 13, 10 respectively)
        Richard Edwards: pp. 644-45: "For Christmas day," extract from The Paradyse of Dainty Devises (1576)
        George Puttenham (?): pp. 754-55: "Puttenham's version of the 'Desire' song," Extract from The Arte of English Poesie (1589) (copied from Edward Arber's edition of 1869)
        Thomas Deloney, Extracts from A Garland of Goodwill (?1593): pp. 756-59 (copied from Percy's Reliques), pp. 796-817B (copied from The Works of Thomas Deloney, ed. F.O. Mann [1912])
        Thomas Watson: pp. 764-65: Sonnet 22 from his Hekatompathia (1582)